Buying a property in Costa Rica, not
easy. I'm a real estate professional who
owns a portfolio of about 70 houses from
Georgia to Washington State, including
destination Airbnbs in Tennessee,
Washington, and Augusta. I co-own a real
estate brokerage and wholesaling
company, and I've been a real estate
professional for over 10 years. Bought
and sold about 400 houses in my life. It
was a tricky process even for me. To
begin with, there's no license required
to sell real estate in Costa Rica. And
there's no national licensing board.
There's no regulation on it. And anybody
who knows somebody with a house for sale
is a real estate agent. Verifiably, go
into any small town in Costa Rica and
tell them you're looking to buy land and
you'll be off. You don't know anything
about real estate in general don't even
attempt this. People who are in the real
estate industry understand about real
estate. They know about title. They know
about closing. They know about finance.
They know about lawyers. They know about
leans. They know about tax deed,
probate. They know these things exist.
If all those terms are foreign to you,
stay the [__] out of Costa Rica. I know
about all this [__] and know about it
intimately. But in Costa Rica, there's a
whole another world of [__] I didn't
know about. The biggest one is water
rights. If you don't have the correct
water rights to a property and you can't
get water, you done. They don't play
about their rivers in Costa Rica. You
are not fit to divert no water from no
river without government approval. If
you buy land and it doesn't have water
rights, the government can take up to
20% of your land in order to allow you
to drill a well. And the permissions
usually take between eight and 10 years.
Whoa. The tikos of Costa Rica are some
of the nicest people in the world. And
some of them are also nefarious. When
you're talking to a little old Costa
Rican farmer and his family, they have
kids everywhere. They're the nicest
people on planet Earth. And they might
have a pipe running from the river
they've been using for 20 years. That
doesn't mean it's legitimate. 2012, they
updated all the government documents
pertaining to the registry and real
estate, and a lot of things changed,
including this water shed. Yes, you
might have water now, but if you get a
permit to build something and the
government comes out and sees it, it's
gone and you're [__] you have no water
and it'll take like 8 years and 20% of
your land to get one. The other one is
surveys. When they changed the [__] in
2012, they updated all of the maps. The
old Costa Rican surveys were all
handdrawn and some of them were pretty
inaccurate back in the day. Changes in
2012 now stipulate they all have to be
digital and the new ones are often a lot
different than the old ones. I looked at
one property that was in actuality 3
acres smaller than it was listed for
sale and the real estate agent had an
old plat he was going off of. The only
way I obtained this information was from
local contacts who had been through it.
There is no way to know this [__]
without going through it. So, if you've
never done anything like this and you
don't have anybody local, you're really
going to get [__] The other thing is
land restrictions. The Costa Ricans do
not play about their trees, bro. You
have to have the proper zoning if you're
going to build something. And even at my
house I bought, I can't cut down any
trees in the back of the property cuz
it's protected by forestry restrictions.
I'll be honest, even I don't know what
the restrictions say. And I'm one who
reads every jot and tit of what applies
to my property before I buy it. But
there's a problem. These are the
forestry restrictions uh on my property.
It is written in old Spanish from a
Costa Rican dialect that I don't really
understand. And it's a lot of legal
ease. I ain't learned this [__] when I
picked up Spanish in the Changang. I
bought this property with these
restrictions because I'm not cutting
down a tree anyways. Like, they didn't
even have to tell me this. But just know
if you have some weird restrictions on
your property, you're gonna have to dig
to find out what they are and get a
[__] translator. One massive
difference between American and Costa
Rican real estate is that most Costa
Rica is cash. Financing really isn't a
thing over there. If you ain't got
money, don't come. And it's not what I
would consider cheap either. It's
comparable to stuff in the US, but you
can find really good deals if you get in
like I did. I bought a 4acre sustainable
homestead with a three-bedroom, two bath
house, four workshops, group bathrooms,
four tilapia ponds, two kamaron ponds,
120 mature fruit bearing trees, over 40
medicinal plants right across from a
river, and 40 acres of chocolate for
$154,000
USD. I would call that Ailio. I also
spent three weeks scouring Costa Rica
like a madman and tapping every resource
I could find through every lens I could,
whether it was social media, WhatsApp,
or the dude on the corner. I walked off
in the night with an alcoholic in those
Rios to go look at threefinkers and left
Alex with a broke down car while she was
surrounded by construction workers with
machetes on her hip. And she was
completely fine. Nobody even said a
cross word to her. Nobody tried to rob
anybody. It's one of the safest places
I've ever been. and the people are
fantastic. Last big thing is the uso
desuel. That means use of the property
and you've got to make sure you're zoned
correctly. I'll be honest, I don't know
everything about us and all the little
knickknacks of it, but I had two
separate attorneys review it and then
three locals heavily involved in real
estate all verify that my [__] was
right. I don't even understand it, but I
know I can do what I want to on my
property and I can't cut down them trees
in the back and I'm fine with that. saw
multiple cases where people bought [__]
without the correct uso due and they
weren't allowed to build anything or
they didn't have water rights even
though they had documentation saying
that they did it was outdated or
incorrect or had small legal errors that
made it inadmissible and sometimes the
real estate agent and the lawyer
involved are complicit. You don't know a
lawyer over there. So the real estate
agent you've been dealing with is
[__] nice as [__] says, "Hey, I got
this guy and he's a great attorney and
he'll take care of you and these dudes
are very nice and very friendly and very
responsive." And then at the end you buy
it and and you find out that that they
they [__] you. Before you close, the
lawyer sends you a due diligence report
with everything in there that he found
and you have to acknowledge and agree.
Once you do that and it goes to closing,
that's it, man. If they had outdated
documents and that's all they had and
you didn't ask for correct documents
because you didn't know you needed them,
it's on you. That's all pre-closing. I'm
going to tell you the worst part of
buying in Costa Rica is [__] escro
approval. You can't wire money into
Costa Rica willy-nilly. It has to go
through anti-terrorism and money
laundering regulation. I don't know why
it took me a minute to get through that
[__] Almost three weeks to be exact.
They requested no less than 14 financial
documents from me. Eight of them had to
be sent from an attorney on a letterhead
and signed. It was a Costa Rican
financial proctological exam. Basically,
given history of Costa Rica and its
location on the cocaine highway and
narco traffic through there, I
understand why they have this, but it
was really a pain in the ass. Kind of
funny. I actually made friends with the
escrow guy that gave me such a hard
time. I can't wait to meet you. on
escrow is the only way to get money into
Costa Rica to buy a property. You got to
go through it. Title. Who's going to own
the property? Is it going to be you or a
corporation? I would always advise you
to buy it in a corporation for a number
of reasons that are outside the scope of
this video. I like a Costa Rican
corporation because you can sell equity
stakes or percentages in it at any time
and bring in partners and also liquidate
them. It moves very fluidly. And the tax
system in Costa Rica is gangster. You
get a registration number for your
corporation that is automatically logged
to the National Registry of Financial
Transactions for their taxes and every
time you buy anything, you give them
that number and it automatically logs it
as an expense instead of you having to
do it at the time of transaction, it's
automatically in there. I've always
formed my own LLC's and plan to do so in
Costa Rica, but the information is all
willy-nilly up and down all around. I
couldn't make sense of it and it's all
in Spanish. government websites with
legal Spanish words. You can hit Google
Translate if you want to, bro. At your
own peril. I paid a lawyer to do it.
Cost about 1,200 bucks. Uh, well worth
it. And I got information that was
invaluable from this attorney. I cannot
emphasize enough getting information
from local people involved in real
estate if you're trying to do this in
Costa Rica. With a corporation, you also
don't have to go back to Costa Rica to
sign a closing. You can just designate a
proxy to sign one time for your
corporation. Save you a lot of time and
hassle. How do you find a property in
Costa Rica? They're pretty [__] easy.
They for sale all over the place. Real
estate, tourism, and agriculture are the
biggest economic activities. Real estate
the most notable. You can look online
for Costa Rican real estate, but it's a
verifiable maze of marketing websites. A
lot of them from reputable agencies like
Keller Williams, and you can find
properties for sale with agents who are
worth their salt. You're going to pay a
premium. And you're also going to find
things in the more populated, dense
cities. Most of the stuff I saw in the
market that was off the beaten path was
not great. Very mountainous property. Uh
stuff without a whole lot of water.
Stuff that was remote with no tourism or
no attractions nearby. You can find what
you think is a fire ass property. 25
acres with a house for 200 grand. That's
amazing. Yeah. Well, it's 19 1/2 acres
of a mountain and there's a creek that
runs down the back, but it's dry half
the year. and all that you can do there
is really grow cows and there's nothing
for miles that exists. The best
properties in Costa Rica rarely hit the
market because they get bought up by
local real estate sharks before they
ever get there. Yet, one slipped through
the cracks. I actually found mine online
and used a realtor named Florian Mode.
He was fantastic to work with. If you
need one down there, reach out. I'll
give you his contact. I also wanted the
protection of having an attorney cuz I
know I didn't know all this [__] And I
realized quickly I was up against a
mountain of information I was completely
ignorant of, which is a rare thing for
me. So I was fine to have help and pay
that commission. Life and real estate
both move slower in Costa Rica than the
States. It took me about 5 weeks to
close and I was pushing as fast as I
could. If you lock up a deal, expect
about 2 months. Closing was easy.
Designated a proxy, wired the bunny,
docuigned everything. We Gucci. And
that's all I know about Costa Rican real
estate is closing. cuz that's as far as
I've gotten. You can see it there. Deal
closed, secure title. My [__] is bought
and paid for. I owe no man no money for
a 4acre sustainable homestead in Costa
Rica. Uh I hope this information has
helped you and come see me down south,
man.